Hello, something different
today, not physiology,
but pathophysiology.
Very important topic,
and today we'll be visiting
acid-base disorders.
My name again,
Dr. Jörg Lindhest.
These are the learning
objectives that go with
the session, and some of
the things, especially
at the beginning, may
seem familiar to you.
I found it necessary
to make the connections
between physiology
and pathophysiology
to briefly go over
some of the highlights
that you have already
covered in week one.
The majority of the session,
however, will be spending
on the four major types
of simple acid-base
disorders and how physicians
determine one or the other.
The pH in our body is very
tightly controlled. And
just as a reminder, the pH
is defined as the negative
decatic logarithm of
hydrogen ion concentration
which in an optimal case is
around 40 nano equivalents
per liter and if we
extrapolate that to our curve
here that will get us to
a blood pH of 7.4 the pH
and intracellular fluid is
slightly lower than that
um a few other things that
you can determine from
this graph so the one is
that there is a ph range
so it's not exactly 7.4
at all times so there's
actually a range that is
determined as normal which is
between 7.35 and 7.45 that's
this range here then if
you follow the curve towards
acidemia, you can see
that this curve is much,
much longer and broader.
So the system responds to
rather large amounts of
changes in hydrogen ions
with comparatively little
change in pH. And that's
because our system has
buffer capacities to deal
with hydrogen ions. In the
past lectures, we talked
about hemoglobin serving
as one of the buffering
elements for hydrogen ions.
Not the same is
true for alkalemia.
So if we have a rise in pH and
an overabundance of
hydroxy ions, the situation
is not the same.
And you can see here
with this curve that
rather small changes
produce a relatively
large difference in pH.
So in other words, our
system is not as well
equipped to deal with OH
ions as it is with H plus
ions. And that's because
as part of metabolism,
we naturally produce more
hydrogen ions. So we're
tending towards acidemia
rather than alkalemia.
Here we are looking at
the kinetics of weak
acids and bases and
briefly explore how we
get to an equation that
combines all of this.
So if we have a weak
acid, in this case HA,
then we have a rate
constant, K1, which describes
the speed by which the
weak acid HA dissociates
into its salts, which
is the hydrogen ion Na-.
Then we have a rate
constant for the same
reaction, but reversed,
and that is K2.
So once we take all of
those four components and
combine those, then we end
up with this formula here and
where k then becomes the
equilibrium constant so k
basically describes the
equilibrium between this process
considering the k1 and
k2 weight constants then
we arrange for hydrogen ion
then we obtain this term
and then we add ph so in
order to do that we have to
add a negative dacatic
logarithmic function to describe
this SPH, and then we end
up with what's known as
the Henderson-Hasselbalch
equation. So basically,
described in words, this is
an equation that equates a
specific pH with a dissociation
rate of a weak acid.
so what is this pka value
that we just encountered
well in terms of formula
it's the negative the chaotic
logarithm of ka which is
the dissociation constant of
a solution and that what
what that means in normal
terms is a measure of how
strong or how weak an acid is
and that is what the pKa
describes. So an acid that
is very strong is down here
on this end between zero
and the pKa of minus four
and that is those are acids
strong acids give off the
hydrogen ions very easily.
Assets on this end
between 10 and 14 are
comparatively weak acids
and there are weak acids
because their tendency
to give off the hydrogen
ions is less pronounced.
So it's more difficult
for them to give off
their hydrogen ions.
Let me just preface
that pKa and pKa are
essentially the same
thing, but that pKa is more
frequently used with
acids and pKa can be
used with any molecule
that is dissociable.
Now we're looking at
the titration curve of a
weak acid here and one
thing that sticks out
immediately is the sigmoid
shape of this curve.
So we have a linear center
and then we have a non
-linear portion in this
direction where we add hydrogen
ions and then we have a
non-linear portion where we
remove them. The shape means
means that this particular
acid buffers the best in
the central portion here.
And that's how acids
and pKs are defined.
They are the point
at which an acid is
most effective in its
buffering capacity.
In this case, this
acid has a pK of 6.5.
If you exceed the hydrogen
ion concentration, then
you get into a nonlinear
portion here, which means
that rather small
additions of hydrogen make
rather large differences
the same in the opposite
direction so here we're
still linear but now we're
not and the withdrawal of
rather small amounts of
hydrogen ions reduce large
effects in this range so
if one wanted to add a
weak acid to a buffering
system or to a system that
needs to be buffered, one
would choose an acid
that has its pK or pKa in
the range of where the
buffering is most essential.
This slide compares
bicarbonate and phosphate
buffers so this bicarbonate
buffer is the one
that is the main buffer
system inside our blood
and um to much lesser
degree we have phosphate
buffering going on um
interestingly while this
bicarbonate buffer is the
dominant buffer it has
a pk that's actually
quite different than our
desired blood pH, which was
around 7.4. So the phosphate
buffer is much closer with
its PK to our blood pH.
Nevertheless, our system
is using and relying on
the bicarbonate buffer
because it's a very elegant
way to transport carbon
dioxide throughout the
body and get rid of it as
a gas. So that is something
that the phosphate
buffer cannot accomplish.
This is a typical acid
-base map that a physician
would use. There are
other ones, such as the
Davenport diagram, but it's
much less frequently used,
so we're not going to
bother with that today.
This acid-base map considers
three types of values.
It considers the blood
partial pressure of CO2. It
considers the abundance of
bicarbonate ion in milliequivalents
per liter, and then at
the same time the pH.
And it's used to figure
out how severe and what the
nature is of an acid-base
disorder. So there is this
line here in yellow, and
there's an oval in the center.
And whatever values are
in this oval is what's
considered normal. So let's
just extrapolate to carbon
dioxide, a value around
40 millimeter mercury in
blood is normal. And at the
same time, a value of 24
milliequivins per liter in
bicarbonate is also normal.
Somebody can have an acid
-base disorder that moves along
the yellow line. So the
yellow line per se is not
something that's necessarily
good. So you can be on the
yellow line and present with
values that are undesirable.
So you can also achieve a
blood pH, which is normal,
at 7.4 by having nearly
48 milliequivalents of
bicarbonate iron, and if I
extrapolate here, of nearly 80
millimeters mercury in
CO2. And while that is
still giving you a pH of
7.4, it's non-physiologic.
acid-base disturbances
can be either metabolic
or they can be
respiratory in nature the
metabolic ones if the
bicarbonate ion concentration
is too low and we're
talking about metabolic
acidosis if it's too
high then we're talking
about metabolic alkalosis
in parallel if blood
partial pressures
of CO2 are too high,
we're talking about
respiratory acidosis. If
those CO2 levels in
blood are too low,
we're talking about
respiratory alkalosis.
Remember both those
molecules, CO2
and bicarbonate,
they're connected
through the bicarbonate
buffer system.
And so there are various
ways, there are two
main ways that the system
can deal with these
aberrations the system can
either deal with it through
respiratory measures
with ventilation blowing
off co2 for instance
in case co2 is too high
or on the other end
the system can use its
kidneys and increase
the excretion of
hydrogen ions or maintain
different levels of
bicarbonate as needed
to cause regulation.
So there's a regulation via gas
and there's a
chemical regulation.
There are four simple
acid-base disorders
and we call them simple because
they're caused by
one thing that's off.
Everything else is
considered mixed acid-base
disorders, and they're
more complex to determine.
But let's get started
with this. So the
four simple acid-base
disorders are metabolic
acidosis, respiratory
acidosis, metabolic
alkalosis, and
respiratory alkalosis.
And you can see that the
primary answer to each
one of those is done by
the opposite system. So, if
we have a respiratory
issue as the primary issue,
the immediate response
is renal compensation. If
we have a metabolic issue
at the root cause, then
the immediate response is
a respiratory response.
So, after the
immediate response,
there's a long-term response.
And just keep in mind that
the system that carries
out the long-term response
is always the kidney.
um it's a good time to get
used to what the normal
values um blood values look
like so we already discussed
the ph a normal blood ph
is around 7.4 um a normal
bicarbonate level is around
24 milliequivalents per
liter a normal p co2 value
is around 40 millimeters
mercury so that never changes
that's always normal and
those three values is
something i need you to know
okay so let's just play
this through um metabolic
acidosis as our first example
is caused by bicarbonate
levels that are too low
they're below 424 milli
equivalents the first
responder is the respiratory
system and it will respond
by lowering its pco2 how do
you lower pco2 um you
increase breathing rate so
you're blowing off um more
co2 with hyperventilation
our second example respiratory
acidosis um this time
the acidosis is caused by
a pco2 that is above 40
millimeters mercury which is
what's normal and the system
that responds primarily and
primarily primary function
is the renal system and
it will then increase the
production or the salvage of
bicarbonate in the kidney.
Now let's move on
to the alkalosis.
The first one is
metabolic alkalosis.
We already know that
because it's metabolic, that
means that something is
wrong with the bicarbonate.
There's too much of it
in the system above 24
milliequivalents. The
primary response must be
respiratory, and the system
will then try to preserve
and get its PCO2 level
above 40 millimeters
mercury and that happens
through hypoventilation.
Then we have respiratory
alkalosis and if that's
the case, then the PCO2
value is above 40 millimeter
mercury and the system in
primary response is the
renal system and it will
respond by lowering the
bicarbonate to below 24
milliequivalents per liter.
So this is the same as
the previous slide in a
tabulated form, maybe a little
bit easier to comprehend.
So here we have
metabolic acidosis and
alkalosis, we already
know that since they're
metabolic, the disturbance
is in the bicarbonate
ion, whereas the
disturbance with the
respiratory counterparts
are in the CO2 levels.
The primary compensation
for metabolic issues
is respiratory, that we
see here, either hyper
or hypoventilation, and
the primary compensation
for respiratory
disturbances is metabolic
or by the kidney, and
that you can see here.
So these responses are
the primary responses.
They're also considered
acute responses, and
then it's important to
remember that the chronic
response of our body
always has to go
through the kidney. So
the chronic response then
leads to the adjustment
of things by the
kidney, either higher
level of excretion of
hydrogen ions or
increased salvage
or production of
bicarbonate ion.
because then the reason
being that hyperventilation
and hyperventilation,
as in this case,
will cause non-physiologic
levels of carbon
dioxide in blood, which
is not a good thing. So
for the kidney to adjust
things back to normal
in a chronic manner, that
takes a few days or up
to a week. But that is
always the end result.
Diagnosis of acid
-base disorders
involves the
termination of ions.
And there are two
main groups of ions in
our body, namely the
positively charged
ones. Those are the
cations, and the most
abundant one in our
bloodstream is sodium.
And then the equivalent
on the negatively
charged N, the N ions, the most
abundant one in our
blood, is chloride.
And then the old familiar
bicarbonate, which
is right here.
Because in order to
be consistent with
life, negative and
positively charged
ions have to be in
balance in the body.
And they're not, if we're
just considering the three
that I just pointed out, we
also have to point out this
group here, which is
responsible for the anion gap.
So those are negatively
charged molecules,
and the largest group of
them are negatively charged
proteins, but also phosphates,
citrate, and sulfates
that are contributing the
missing negative charges.
So looking at the anion
gap at its size and
its composition is
particularly useful in
the diagnosis of certain
metabolic acidosis.
And one example,
which we will talk
about in a little
while, is diabetes.
So that's when
this anion gap is
very useful for
diagnostic purposes.
To be able to determine
the plasma anion gap is
essential for working
with acid-base disorders.
So the normal anion
gap, or the range
of the normal anion
gap, is between
8 and 14 milliequivalents
per liter.
And here's how you do it.
So the plasma anion
gap equals the sodium
concentration. In this case,
it's 140 milliequivalents
per liter minus the
sum of the bicarbonate
concentration, which is 24
milliequivalents per liter.
Again, that's a value that
you should know by now.
Plus the chloride
concentration, which is 104
milliequivalents per
liter. So what we have to
do is add the 24 to
the 104, which is 128
milliequivalents per liter.
And so we have 128 here,
and we deduct that from
140, and we end up with
an anion gap of 12
milliequivalents per liter,
which according to our
range here is normal.
most acid-base disorders
that you will encounter
throughout your education
and also career will
be metabolic acidosis
with an increased nion gap
these are all causes for
it and while i'm only
holding you accountable
to those that we'll talk
about in more detail
later on in the lecture
i'm giving you this here
for completeness sakes.
What do these all have
in common? Well, all of
these molecules are anions.
So that means that they're
negatively charged, such
as bicarbonate, which
is negatively charged.
And the only way for our
body to ensure electroneutrality
is to get rid of
its bicarbonate causing
the metabolic acidosis.
The only few cases where
we're dealing with an osmolar
gap that is a discrepancy
between observed and
measured values of charged
substances this happens
in methanol and ethylene
glycol poisoning and the
reason why this is happening
is that they have an
extremely low molecular
weight so that produces this
error and that's all you have
to know at this point the
fact that knife is frequently
more complex than it
needs to be is also true
for acid-base disorders.
And that concept is nowhere
truer than a second hidden
metabolic acid-base disorder
on top of another one.
So now we're talking about
a complex disease and we're
talking about various factors
that overlay each other.
So in order to figure
things out physicians use
a tool that's called
the delta delta tool and
delta means change so it
looks at the change of
bicarbonate and in relation
to the change of the
anion gap so if we only
have one metabolic disease
or one metabolic acidosis
for instance with an
increased iron gap the
decrease in blood bicarbonate
is the same as the
increase in the anion gap.
If a second metabolic
disorder is overlaying
the first and it goes
into the opposite
direction, such as a
metabolic alkalosis,
then we're looking at a
decrease in blood bicarbonate
from the first, from
the primary disease, and
then the secondary
subtracts from it because it
goes into the opposite
direction, which means that
the observed blood
bicarbonate level that we
see is smaller than the
increase in the anion gap.
The opposite is true if
the two disorders that
occur at the same time go
into the same direction.
So then we not only
observe the decrease in
blood bicarbonate from
the first, but also from
the secondary, which
overlay each other, which
means that the blood
bicarbonate that we observe
is larger than the
increase in the anion gap.
So again, this is a
difficult concept, and it's
probably going to take a
moment until you're able to
wrap your heads around
this, but we're going do
examples and hopefully that'll
make it easier for you.
For completeness sakes,
we need to look at
the only one case in
which we observe a
metabolic acidosis with
a normal anion gap.
You can see from the graph
that both sides, positive
and negatively charged
ions, are in balance, but
you can also see that the
bicarbonate has decreased
in concentration as
indicated by the blue arrow.
However, the void
that is made up by the
decrease in bicarbonate
ions is filled by an
overabundance of
negatively charged chloride
ions, which is the only
other measured anion.
So the increase in chloride
ions, in other words,
is masking the decrease
in bicarbonate ions. and
that is for making for
this very special case in
which we have a metabolic
acidosis as defined by the
reduction in bicarbonate
with a normal anion gap.
This graph is giving
a quick overview
over a patient's
acid-based status
and it is a quick means
to look at things and
get a basic idea but
it's not something that
a physician would use to
make a final determination
That works with numbers,
and those examples
we'll do in the
remainder of the lecture.
So here we have our yellow
line, which indicates normal.
I mean, it's normal
in terms of pH.
However, if one is not
exactly in this oval zone,
that means that both either
one or both, either CO2 or
bicarbonate, are too high
or too low. So this line
just means that the optimal
pH has been achieved,
blood pH of 7.40, but those
two molecules that we're
considering, CO2 and
bicarbonate, might still be off.
Anything that's below is
acidosis, or I'm sorry,
anything that's below
NPH is up here, that's
acidosis. And anything
that's above 7
.4 NPH is down here,
and that is alkalosis.
You also see that there
is only one response for
metabolic acidosis and one
for metabolic alkalosis,
alkalosis, but there's
two for their respiratory
counterparts. The reason being
is that metabolic acidosin
and alkalosis are
compensated for immediately
via respiratory action.
So with the respiratory
alkalosin acidosis, there is
an acute response, and this
is the acute response
for respiratory acidosis
and then there is the chronic
response which goes into
the same direction but
is off a little bit so
there's something that the
kidney can do immediately
and then everything else
as we've already heard
follows with a few days or a
week delay the same is true
for the acute and chronic
respiratory alkalosis.
I'm sorry, this is, yes,
this is alkalosis down here.
So we previously talked
about the delta-delta
technique that would
allow us to determine
whether we're dealing
with a simple acid-base
disorder or with one
that is overlaying it.
So in order to make
that determination
and use the delta
-delta technique, we
have to use the so
-called renal rules.
And they're used
for the prediction
of compensatory responses
that can overlay simple
acid-base disorders.
So this seems very
cryptic, but no worry, I
will take you through it
and we'll do examples.
So what's important
is this, what's most
important is this column. So
the predicted compensatory
response. So here you
can see, for instance,
for metabolic acidosis,
that we're expecting
for one milliequivalent
per liter change,
in this case, decrease
of bicarbonate,
we're expecting an
equivalent decrease of 1
.2 millimeters mercury
in carbon dioxide.
So this column will allow
us to calculate what to
expect in terms of the
relationship between bicarbonate
and CO2, and that's true
for all of those diseases.
So this is our first example of
metabolic alkalosis,
which is defined as
an increase in
bicarbonate in blood.
So that's one thing.
It also is accompanied
by an increase of
partial pressure of CO2
and by an increased pH.
So how can this happen? Well,
those are three main causes.
The one cause of
an increased pH
is the loss of
fixed hydrogen ions.
And there are two reasons
that can cause this,
which is excessive
vomiting, for instance,
and hyperaldosteronism.
That's a multi-step
process. We don't need to
go into detail, but
those two are associated
with excessive losses
of fixed hydrogen ion.
And if they get lost,
then blood pH increases.
Another common reason
are certain medications,
so medications that are taken
for heartburn, for instance,
they're very rich
in carbonic acid and
that then dissociates
into bicarbonate and
raising bicarbonate
levels and with that
pH and increased
partial pressure of CO2.
Lastly, there's
something that's
known as volume
contraction alkalosis.
So that is done by
loop or thiazide
diuretics to treat
high blood pressure.
So indirectly, those increase
the reabsorption
of bicarbonate.
The problem is that the
body is losing volume.
So that's where the volume
contraction comes in. And
in order to hold on to as
much volume as possible,
the body holds on to
also to bicarbonate which
because of its charge
it should get rid of but
it doesn't because that's
at that point its only
way to hold on to the
water inside the body so
those are the three main
reasons that can cause
metabolic alkalosis so
let's do our first case
so here we have a 36 year
old female who's had been
vomiting for three days
and was taken to emergency
department where the following
blood values were measured.
She had a pH of 77.5, a pCO2
of 48, and a bicarbonate,
blood bicarbonate of 37
milliequivalents per liter.
All of these values are
high, and I plotted them
here, and she's in this
range here. So with her
bicarbonate, her CO2, and
the pH, she fits right here,
which identifies her condition
as metabolic alkalosis.
It's not too surprising
because we can
already see that the
pH value is high.
What's interesting
to note, though, is
that her condition
or her values are on
this strip here of
metabolic alkalosis.
And if you remember
what I indicated before,
then that should further
indicate that this
is a simple disorder and
not a mixed disorder.
But let's be sure and
do the calculations.
I know this looks
intimidating, but no worries, I
will take you through. It's
actually fairly simple.
One disclaimer, the numbers
that I used for this
example in Constanzo are
faulty, so I fixed them.
They come to the same
conclusion, yet different
numbers are confusing,
so stick with my numbers.
And so we know already that
this patient is suffering
from metabolic alkalosis.
You can see that by
looking here at the renal
rules table. We have
an elevated bicarbonate
it's elevated by 30
milliequivalents per liter
and we have an elevated pCO2
which is elevated by 8
millimeters mercury if
that is the case then
what we need to do is
multiply the increase
in bicarbonate by 0.6
millimeter to get to the
calculated amount of pCO2.
So what we do is multiply
13 milliequivalents per
liter times 0.6 millimeter
mercury and that calculates
us a value of 7.8
millimeter mercury of pCO2.
So the calculated
which is this value and
the observed which
is that value they're
super close and that
confirms our diagnosis.
So the interpretation
of this is
we have an expected respiratory
compensation for a simple
metabolic alkalosis
and this was our
first example and
with the other examples
you use some of the
other rows but I'll
take you through it.
So this is our case of
metabolic alkalosis and these
are the events that are
leading to the observed
condition so we had with our
patient excessive vomiting
over a long period of time
that depletes hydrogen
ions because there's a
lot of them inside the
stomach being released now
that so much hydrogen ion
has been lost to vomiting
the chyme that comes from
the stomach into the small
intestine at duodenum is
lacking hydrogen ion and
so that means then if the
pancreas that's right there
does not sense an acidic
environment it will not
grab bicarbonate from the
blood and put it into
the into the chyme and so
this this lack of grabbing
bicarbonate from the blood
and putting it into the
GI tract raises blood pH.
So that is what we're
observing in our patient.
Now, as the next step,
there's buffering
going on because the
extracellular fluid, which
in this case is our
blood, is high in pH.
So, and as this blood
serves target tissues, those
target tissues will
release hydrogen ion to
facilitate the buffering
of blood. Now they cannot
just release hydrogen ion
because it's a positively
charged ion and to
conserve or preserve
electroneutrality these
cells then need to take up
another cation ion and
that's typically potassium.
So not only do we observe
an increase in pH in this
patient but very likely
also hypokalemia so that
usually goes together with
metabolic alkalosis as in
our case because this
disease is metabolic in
nature you know already
that the primary or acute
compensation happens via
respiratory means what would
need to be done is to
preserve carbon dioxide how do
you do that well the answer
is right here through
hypoventilation and that
increases pco2 if you recall
the bicarbonate buffer
system if you add co2 on
the left side then that
eventually you know has an
effect on the other side
and And where carbonic
acid dissociates into
bicarbonate and hydrogen ions.
And if you push towards
that end and keep
pushing through conservation
of CO2, that will
slowly but surely
lower the pH, blood pH.
But we already know that
this is just a primary
response or the acute
response. the chronic
response will be
through renal correction
that'll take a few days
and the kidney usually
does that through increased
bicarbonate excretion
until the normal state
has been achieved.
So with metabolic
alkalosis due to vomiting
we easily end up in a
catch-22 two situation
and I will explain
to you what I mean.
So we've already seen
that the loss of gastric
hydrochloride leads to a
loss of fixed hydrogen ion,
which gives rise to the
observed metabolic alkalosis.
At the same time, we
get volume contraction.
So if we have so much of a
loss of charged molecules,
then our body is trying
to hold onto water by
using those charged
molecules is no longer able
to do that. So when that
is being sensed, our
body produces angiotensin
2 and aldosterone.
Those are hormones that
are released to increase
ECF volume, so to
hold on to water. And
what happens is that
sodium is being preserved.
Now the problem here is that
sodium can only be preserved
by the kidney in exchange
for hydrogen ion so as
we preserve sodium the
system throws out even more
hydrogen ion and as a result
of that there is an increased
reabsorption tied to that
of filtered bicarbonate
so this cements in the
metabolic alkalosis that we have
been observing already the
effects of aldosterone are
very similar so as a result
of aldosterone stimulation
we see a hydrogen ion
secretion and reabsorption of
bicarbonate so the basically
the same thing is happening
with aldosterone as it is
with angiotensin further
cementing in metabolic
acidosis plus another effect
of aldosterone is that it
leads to potassium secretion
in the kidney and that
will further cement in the
hypokalemia that we are
already seeing with our patient
some of these cases are
saline sensitive so if you
provide saline supplementation
some respond to this
you can fix the volume
contraction with that some
cases are not which is which
and what exact medications
are used you'll discuss
with our clinical faculty.
So now we're turning our
attention to the next
disorder and this is the
most common one that you will
encounter in your career
it's metabolic acidosis
it's signified by a decreased
bicarbonate constant
blood bicarbonate concentration
that goes together
with decreased pH and also
decreased pCO2 the causes
can be manifold so but
there are different classes
of what can happen so one
is the excessive reduction
or ingestion of fixed
hydrogen ions. We see that
a lot in diabetic ketoacidosis
and lactic acidosis.
Salisade poisoning
would be aspirin
poisoning and some
other conditions.
It can result from the
mishandling of bicarbonate.
That can happen
or most commonly
happens as a
result of diarrhea.
A renal condition
that will do the same
thing is type 2 renal
tubular acidosis.
So here we have the inability
of the recapture
of bicarbonate.
the same can happen
with hydrogen ions so in
the inability of
secreting and excreting
hydrogen ions into the
urine that is known to
come with chronic kidney
diseases type 1 and 4
and all of that can be the
cause of metabolic acidosis
Well, let's do a calculation
case. This is our
second case, and this time
on diabetic ketoacidosis.
I would like to
read this to you.
A 56-year-old female
presents with a 15-year
history of type 1 diabetes
mellitus, which has
been controlled by careful
dietary monitoring and
treatment with subcutaneous
injections of insulin
twice a day. A recent
viral illness has
resulted in loss of appetite,
fever, and vomiting.
She becomes short of
breath and is admitted
to the intensive care
unit of the hospital.
Physical examination
reveals that the woman
is acutely ill. Her
mucous membranes are
dry, and she has
decreased skin turgor.
She's breathing deeply
and rapidly, and a
urine sample contains
glucose and ketones. That
should not be a big
surprise at this point.
Here the laboratory tests,
and we have these values
in the material blood,
and then these ions in
venous plasma, so the pH
is too low, the pCO2 is too
low, as well as the
bicarbonate being too low, and
these are the ion levels,
and this is glucose.
Let's look at the calculations
and see where we are.
So let's now calculate
this example.
So this is a case of
metabolic acidosis,
which we already know
from the low blood pH.
And we're going to use the
renal rules and the delta
-delta method to determine
whether this is a simple or
mixed acid-base disorder.
and so here are the normal
values again compared to
that our patient has a low
bicarbonate blood bicarbonate
and the low pCO2 all
three of them low bicarbonate
low pCO2 paired with the
low pH we know that this
is metabolic acidosis then
we look up this number here
with which we need to multiply
our bicarbonate value
let's do that now so we're
multiplying 19 milliequivalents
per liter by 1.2 that's
from the renal rules table
for metabolic acidosis
and the calculated value for
pCO2 is 22.8 the observed
is 22 and they're close
enough to determine that
this is a simple metabolic
acidosis and that we can
expect, together with the
interpretation of this,
a respiratory compensation.
And we're actually seeing
this in this patient because
the patient is breathing
deeply and rapidly. And that
means that the patient is
by doing that trying to
blow off co2 at the one end
of the bicarbonate buffer
system and so that pulls the
whole system to the left
and hydrogen ions out of the
system so blowing off co2
on one end also reduces the
amount of hydrogen ions on
the other end so that's the
explanation for a breathing
pattern let's now briefly
look at the anion gap in
this patient so here is the
formula to calculate the
anion gap once again make sure
that you resolve this term
first and then subtract
it from sodium if we do that
and we have all the numbers
here we end up with 33
milliequivalent per liter of
anions normal is 8 to 16 so
we have a large anion gap
that's not really surprising
because this glucose
level here is not good
so and as a result as the
result of ketoacidosis
tied to diabetes we expect
and that's what the urine
panel would confirm high
levels of beta-hydroxybutyrate
and acetoacetate
which are the result of
this very large anion gap.
So let me now take you
through the sequence of
events in metabolic acidosis.
So we have a gain of
fixed hydrogen ions through
the patient's condition.
That excess of hydrogen
ion is buffered with
bicarbonate in the ECF,
meaning in the blood, that
titers bicarbonate away
so and that is responsible
for the drop in bicarbonate
in the blood also the
cells that this blood is
serving they are affected
so the excess hydrogen
ion enters the cells and
then it's buffered by
organic compounds and
proteins inside the cell
in intracellular fluid
And to achieve
electroneutality, the cells
that take up hydrogen
ion, which is a
cation, have to
release another cation.
In this case, as with
the example before, it's
potassium that's affected.
But this time, potassium,
instead of being taken up into
cells, it's being released
into the bloodstream. And
very often with metabolic
acidosis, for that reason,
we see hyperkalemia.
Then we have respiratory
compensation. So, the acidic
blood environment is being
sensed by chemoreceptors
in the carotid artery. So,
they're more sensitive to
that than the ones that
are in the aortic arch. and
so that is then responsible
for her deep but fast
breathing that blows off CO2
as I already indicated which
then normalizes the pH on
the other end but of course
our pCO2 is already low
so this acute compensation
is not the desired end result
and for that reason then
the chronic system sets in
where the kidney actively
has to secrete hydrogen ion
it does that as ammonium
ion and the kidney also
increases recovery and also
the production of bicarbonate
to fix the low levels
let's now explore acid
-base disorders from
the respiratory end and
we're going to start
with respiratory
acidosis, and respiratory
acidosis is caused by an
increased pCO2, and that
typically happens
through hypoventilation.
The arterial blood profile
looks like that, so
we have a decreased pH
because we keep adding
CO2 on one end that leads
to the production of
bicarbonate and And
hydrogen ion on the other,
so that's what we see,
increased bicarbonate,
increased PCO2, and
also a drop in pH.
Now, how can this happen?
Well, it can happen
centrally, and that's usually
through drugs acting on
the medullary respiratory
center in the brainstem.
So examples are
opiates, barbiturates,
anesthetics. There
can be lesions.
One thing that's gaining
more and more attention
is sleep apnea, so more
and more people are
suffering from sleep apnea,
not breathing enough,
not breathing deeply
enough, buildup of CO2.
It can result from
certain disorders
that affect
respiratory muscles.
First and foremost,
Guillain-Barre, polio,
ALS, multiple
sclerosis, those are
all things that you
will discuss with
our clinical faculty
in more detail.
Airway obstruction,
already mentioned,
obstructive sleep apnea,
the other ones that are rare
are laryngeal spasm aspirations
could be indicative of
a buildup of fluid that
prevents proper gas exchange.
This would also fit here.
Disorders of gas exchange
that commonly lead to
respiratory acidosis a COPD
remember that inflammation that
comes with COPD destroys
primarily elastic tissues
so the air that has
been inspired cannot
be efficiently released
so the old air sits
there and that can also
lead to an increase
in pCO2 and cause
respiratory acidosis
Let's now do the
sequence of events
and respiratory
acidosis together.
So for one of the
reasons that we
looked at, we see
retention of CO2.
That's typically the case due
to some form of
hypoventilation.
So that increases the pCO2,
and if we keep adding CO2
on one end of the bicarbonate
buffer system we get an
increase of bicarbonate and
hydrogen ion on the other
and because of the hydrogen
ion we get a drop in pH
so um with the so one of the
consequences is then that
cells that are served
by this bloodstream they
try to buffer some of this
hydrogen ion by taking
it up into the cells
and um by binding it to
large proteins and
organic organic phosphates
in order to do that the
cells need to release a
cation if they take hydrogen
ion and in many cases
we have we see hyperkalemium
um in those patients um
here once we again we
have the function of the
bicarbonate buffer system,
and I made a point here
because I wanted to reiterate
that while all of these
substances are considered
freely dissolved in
plasma, they are tied to
the red blood cells, and
that's because the red
blood cells are the location
of the carbonic anhydrase,
which carries out all
of those conversions, CO2
and water, into carbonic
acid and also a carbonic
acid into bicarbonate and
hydrogen ion and it does
that forward and reverse
um there's no respiratory
compensation because
the original issue is
respiratory in nature
we do see renal compensation
and remember there's
acute and chronic acutely
we see that the kidneys will
start to excrete more
ammonium ion to get rid of
the H plus and to buffer
more of the hydrogen ion
despite the fact that we
have already elevated values
the kidney will recover
an increased production of
bicarbonate so because that's
a very effective buffer
for hydrogen ions once
that is accomplished um
the the chronic effects
have to set in um to reduce
the elevated bicarbonate
levels and as always that
can take a few days um you
can also apply this example
to the renal rules table
and the delta delta that
that we've done before
um i would ask you to do
this on your own time though
the methodology is fairly
easy and we've done it
for the metabolic diseases
so let's finish up with
respiratory alkalosis
which is defined by the
excessive loss of carbon
dioxide through
hyperventilation that goes with
the loss of bicarbonate
and an increased blood ph
now this can happen
in three ways a
through the stimulation
of the medullary
respiratory center
that we talked about.
One condition where this
happens is known as hysterical
hyperventilation, so that's
the increased breathing
frequency as a result of
fear. It can happen through
bacterial infection and
especially through the
travel of LPS of gram-negative
bacteria to the medulla.
salisade poisoning
again, too much aspirin
can also result from
tumor or stroke.
Then it can result from
hypoxemia. We already talked
about high altitude sickness
that would cause this,
hyperventilation, and also
mechanical ventilation.
So when a mechanical
ventilator is misadjusted,
then respiratory alkalosis
can also be the result.
So here's the
sequence of events.
An excessive loss of
CO2 will, of course,
decrease the hydrogen ion
concentration and with it
the bicarbonate concentration,
which increases the pH.
Then intracellular fluids
will try to buffer this And
then we'll release carbon
dioxide into the bloodstream
with the drawback that the
intracellular pH goes up.
There's no respiratory
compensation for this
condition because it's
respiratory in nature.
and but we do get renal
compensation which will
focus on the decrease of
hydrogen ion excretion
and also the recovery of
carbon of bicarbonate again
keep in mind that the
acute and chronic effects
and that it can take a few
days until the body has
adjusted another board
start question for you a
24 year old male is
brought to the emergency
department after being found
unresponsive in his apartment
a rapid clinical workup
is initiated and his
basic metabolic panel and
arterial blood gas you know
the following values
the next ones are in
milliequivalents per liter
that sodium 140 chloride 105
bicarbonate 15 we have an
arterial blood pH of 7.8
that's low and a partial
pressure of carbon dioxide
of 32 millimeters mercury
which of the following
options correctly calculates
his plasma anion gap and
correctly identifies his
pathophysiological state
let's just quickly do
the calculation of the
anion gap which is
calculated as the combined
value um concentration
value of chloride thus
bicarbonate minus the
concentration of sodium
So chloride is 105,
bicarbonate is 15
milliequivalents
per liter, that
together is 120.
Then we subtract 120
from the value of
sodium, which is 140,
and we end up with 20.
So that indicates that
A is wrong, because 10
milliequivalents per liter
is actually a normal Ni-gap
value. That's between 8
and 12, but it's true that
diarrhea can cause a normal
anion gap metabolic acidosis
because bicarbonate is
lost from the GI tract.
um b anion gap of 20 milli
equivalence per liter
indicating a normal anion gap
metabolic acidosis secondary
to renal tubular acidosis
so the the calculated value
of 20 milli equivalence per
liter is correct but that
we already know is not a
normal um but a high anion
gap metabolic acidosis making
this answer choice wrong
it is true that secondary
to renal tubular acidosis
we do see normal anion gap
metabolic acidosis it's
actually one of the prime
examples and that is the reason
because in this condition
bicarbonate is lost from
the kidney and that then
systemically increases the
concentration of chloride ion
to make up for that loss d
and i got of 35 milli
equivalents per liter indicated
a mixed respiratory acidosis
and metabolic alkalosis
so we already know that
35 is the wrong value
plus looking at his
measured values a pH of 7.28
and the low bicarbonate
level that we see is
actually a sign of a
primary metabolic acidosis
with respiratory compensation
rather than mixed.
Choice E, Ni gap
of 5 mEq per liter
indicating a profound
hypoalbuminemia with
no true primary acid
-base disturbance.
You know, again, the number
is wrong um but you know
severe hypoalbuminemia can
cause um and can cause uh
can cause this condition
because um albumin after
all is the primary unmeasured
iron but once again
the low blood pH that we
see in this patient plus
the wrongly calculated
anion gap make this answer
choice wrong. So that leaves
us with answer choice C.
And so what we see here
is we have the correct
value of 20
milliequivalents per liter.
And we have a high
anion gap because
it's above 12
milliequivalents per liter.
We have acidosis because
of the low pH of 7.28.
And that is typically in
this condition due to the
accumulation of lactic acid
or acetoacetate or beta
-hydroxy butyrate or
other metoxic metabolites
that accumulate in the
blood and thus consume the
bicarbonate buffer needing
to the observed low pH.
I know this thing is a
mouthful. It's not an easy
question, but you can work
yourself through with the
information that you have,
and i hope this to be helpful
once again i want to make
sure that i remind you
one more time of the resources
that are in constanzo so
there's a great summary
section at the end of um of
this chapter um there's
self-quizzing questions with
answers at the end plus we
have scholar x questions
there are numerous examples
out there with which you
can practice your calculations
do them the same way by
using the renal rules table
and the delta delta method
that we have used for our
first two examples and
all that is remaining
at this point is to
say thank you for
listening working with me
please leave me some
feedback. Here's
the link. I hope to
see you soon. Bye.